Finding Aid for Laurie Palazzolo Horn Man research materials collection, 1913-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Laurie Palazzolo Horn Man research materials collection 1913-2004 1940s-1980s
Palazzolo, Laurie, collector.
2009136 Aa 2; UAl
Research materials used by Laurie Palazzolo in writing of her book Horn Man: the Polish-American Musician in Twentieth-Century Detroit (Detroit, Mich.: American-Polish Music Society, 2003). The collection sheds light on the history of 20th century Polish-American musical landscape of greater Detroit.
10 linear feet in 13 boxes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Laurie Palazzolo (donor no. 9936 ) in 2009.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Polish folk music bands were a prominent feature of the 20th century greater Detroit's cultural scene. They performed in dance halls, music clubs, as well as at Polish traditional weddings and funerals.
Laurie Palazzolo is daughter and biographer of Ted Gomulka (1919-1998), and biographer of Stanley Adamus (1922-1988), Eddie Nabozny Hoyt (1917-1999) and Helen Nabozny (1919-), Johnny Sadrack (1919-1989), Ted Koltowicz (1927-2000), Stas Wisniach, and other Polish-American musicians.
Ted Gomulka was a prominent Polish-American folk musician of the 20th century. He was a virtuoso trumpet player, arranger and leader of one of the most popular West-side Polish folk music orchestras. Palazzolo titled her book Horn Man after her father. Stanley Adamus was a West-side orchestra leader and one of the most innovative Polish-American musicians of the Polka Era in Detroit. Eddie Nabozny was a self-taught musician, composer, vocalist, and a band leader. His wife Helen Nabozny was one of the few female Polish-American band leaders in Detroit. Johnny Sadrack was a West-side musician, vocalist, composer, arranger, and a radio show host. Ted Koltowicz was an accomplished East-side accordionist, band leader, composer, and radio program host. The collection contains biographical information about these and a number of other Polish-American polka musicians.
Palazzolo is a founding member of the West Side Detroit Polish American Historical Society and a past officer on the board of directors of the Friends of Polish Art. She is also a president, executive producer of Hornman Detroit, and member of various Polish American cultural and historical organizations. Palazzolo currently serves as the West Side Detroit Polish American Historical Society's Vice President & Executive Director/Secretary.
The collection documents the history and repertoire of Polish folk music bands in the greater Detroit area as well as professional careers of musicians. The records date primarily from the 1940's until 1980s. Materials dated 1990s-2000s are primarily transcripts of interviews taken by Gomulka Palazzolo. Records include correspondence, business contracts, performance schedules and programs, sheet music, scanned copies of photographs, copies of Keynote magazine, biographical information and interviews of musicians, performance advertisements, and recordings. The records are arranged into five series as follows: Research files, Detroit Federation of Musicians, Sheet music, Sound recordings, and Visual materials.
Subjects:
Adamus, Stanley, 1922-1988.; Gomulka, Ted, 1919-1998.; Nabozny, Eddie Hoyt, 1917-1999.; Nabozny, Helen, 1919-; Sadrack, Johnny.; Wisniach, Stan, 1923-2007.; Detroit Federation of Musicians.; Dance music.; Musicians--Michigan--Detroit.; Polish American musicians--Michigan--Detroit--Biography.; Polish Americans--Michigan--Detroit--Biography.; Polkas.; Detroit (Mich.)--History.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Wisniach, Stan, 1923-2007.; Polish National Alliance of the United States of North America.; Dance music.; Music--Michigan--Detroit.; Musicians--Michigan--Detroit.; Polish Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Polkas.
Contributors: Visual Materials
Adamus, Greg.; Bowen, Ralph.; Radzialowski, Thaddeus Casmir.; Wisniach, Stan, 1923-2007.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Gomulka, Ted, 1919-1998.; Sadrach, Johnny.; Wisniach, Stan, 1923-2007.; Michigan Polka-Tels (Musical group); Dance music.; Polish Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Polkas.
Genre Terms:
DVDs.; Oral histories.; Photographs.; Posters.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Research files
  The Research files series includes a six volume Chronology of research materials used in the creation of Horn Man: the Polish-American Musician in Twentieth-Century Detroit (1925-1989) that contains scanned photographs of performances and band members, business correspondence, photocopies and original copyright certificates, business contracts, records of financial transactions, performance programs, and newspaper clippings. The series includes profiles of individual musicians that contain scanned photographs, clippings and in some cases concise biographical information, and transcripts of interviews that were taken by Gomulka Palazzolo in 1998-2001. Also included is material describing cultural influences that provided impact on the development of Polish-American polka music.
  - Chronology of research materials used in the creation of Horn Man: the Polish-American Musician in Twentieth-Century Detroit
    - Vol. 1 1925-1953 (Box 1)
    - Vol. 2 1954-1957 (Box 1)
    - Vol. 3 1958-1963 (Box 2)
    - Vol. 4 1964-1967 (Box 2)
    - Vol. 5 1968-1977 (Box 2)
    - Vol. 6 1978-1989 (Box 2)
  - People file
    - Adamus, Stanley, 2 volumes (Box 3)
    - Budny, Chester (Box 3)
    - Chrzasz, John (Box 3)
    - Cieslik, Walt (Box 3)
    - Duda, Wally (Box 3)
    - Gajec, Eddie (Box 3)
    - Gajec, John (Box 3)
    - Gomulka, Ted, 1 volumes; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Gomulka, Tom (Box 3)
    - Gomulka, Wally (Box 3)
    - Gordon (Gorczyca), Ted (Box 3)
    - Grabowski, Frank (Box 3)
    - Grzesik, Walter Steve (Box 3)
    - Koltowicz, Ted (Box 3)
    - Koltyk, Silven (Box 3)
    - Kustodowich, John (Box 3)
    - Lach, Ted (Box 3)
    - Lipiec, Walt (Box 3)
    - Nabozny (Hoyt), Eddie and Helen (Box 3)
    - Sadrack, Johnny (Box 3)
    - Schik (Krzyk), Eddie (Box 3)
    - Skrzynski, Frank and Mike (Box 3)
    - Skuta, Earnie (Box 3)
    - Smith (Kowal), Frank (Box 3)
    - Wisniach, Stas, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 3)
    - Witkovski, Clarence (Box 3)
    - Zarski, Leon (Box 3)
    - Zurke, Bob (Box 3)
  - Interviews
    - A (Box 4)
    - B (Box 4)
    - C (Box 4)
    - D (Box 4)
    - Gajec (Box 4)
    - Glotzhober-Guzik (Box 4)
    - J-K (Box 4)
    - S-T (Box 4)
    - Washington-Waske (Box 4)
    - Wisniach (Box 4)
    - Witkowski (Box 4)
    - Wozniak-Zielinski (Box 4)
  - Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous
    - The Chadsey Band (Box 4)
    - Hamtramck (Box 4)
    - International Polka Convention (Box 4)
    - The Polish Falcons (Box 4)
    - West side night life (Box 4)
    - News paper clippings, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Cultural influences (Box 5)
    - Big Band and American influence (Box 5)
    - Cultural Blending (Box 5)
    - The Polish culture (Box 5)
    - Address book (Box 5)
- Detroit Federation of Musicians
  The Detroit Federation of Musicians (DFM) series includes DFM's Local No. 5 constitution and by-laws, membership directories, price lists, and photocopies of The Keynote newsletter (1949-1954).
  - Local No. 5
    - Constitution and by-laws 1956, 1974, 1977, 1988 (Box 5)
    - Membership directory
      - 1957, 1976, undated (Box 5)
      - 1983, 1986, 1989 (Box 5)
      - 1991/1992-1995/1996 1999-2000 (Box 5)
    - Price list 1963-1964, 1974, 1977, 1979-1980, 1989, 1991; wage list and by-laws, 1998 (Box 5)
  - American Federation of Musicians of the United States and Canada by-laws 1940 (Box 5)
  - The Keynote, 1949-1954, 2004, 6 folders (Box 5)
- Sheet music
  The Sheet music series consists of collections of manuscript and printed sheet music from Ted and Ruth Gomulka's, Ted Lach's, and Eddie Nabozny Hoyt's personal collections. The series contains early Polish-American music study books, printed sheet music and handwritten compositions.
  - Eddie Nabozny Hoyt's music library, 2 volumes (Box 6)
  - Eddie Nabozny Hoyt's music library (cont.), 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Ted and Ruth Gomulka's songs (Box 7)
  - Ted Lach's music library, 2 folders (Box 7)
- Sound recordings
  The Sound recordings series contains 78-rpm, 45-rpm, and 33 1/2- rpm records of dances and compositions performed by various Polish folk music orchestras, as well as audio cassettes and a CD-ROM with recordings of radio shows, performances, and interviews. Material in this series is arranged in alphabetical order by author or performer. Many of these recordings have been digitized and reissued in the CD collection "American Polish Music from Detroit."
  - 45-rpm phonograph discs
    - Ampol Aires orchestra, 3 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Benny Boc and his orchestra, 3 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Chester Budny & his boys, 5 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Chester Budny orchestra, 2 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Dyna-Dukes orchestra, 3 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Ted Gomulka orchestra, 7 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Kingsmen, 1 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Ted Koltowicz and his sparks of fire orchestra, 1 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Ted Koltowicz and orchestra, 1 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Judge Kotulski polka, 1 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Joseph Kuciemba, 3 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Frank Kurzawa, 2 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Little Joe's Polka Playboys, 1 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Ted Loch & orchestra, 2 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Michigan Polka-Tels, 1 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Eddie Nabozny, 3 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Johnny Nogaj and his orchestra, 1 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - The Polish Muslims: Yuletide Rock Opera, 1 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - The Polka Dots, 9 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Johnny Sadrack and his orchestra, 3 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Art Walunas and his orchestra, 3 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Stan Wisniach and his orchestra, 3 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Stan Wisniach and his TV polka band, 3 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Clare Witkowski and his orchestra, 2 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
    - Unidentified, 6 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 8)
  - 78-rpm phonograph discs
    - Auto city orchestra, 1 phonograph records 78 rpm (Box 9)
    - Gomulka polka band, 5 phonograph records 78 rpm (Box 9)
    - Ted Gomulka orchestra, 8 phonograph records 78 rpm (Box 9)
    - Eddie Nabozny and his orchestra, 1 phonograph records 78 rpm (Box 9)
    - Johnny Sadrack and his orchestra, 11 phonograph records 78 rpm (Box 9)
    - Stan Wisniach and his Polish all stars, 8 phonograph records 78 rpm (Box 9)
    - Peter Uryga and his orchestra, 1 phonograph records 78 rpm (Box 9)
    - Unidentified, 1 phonograph records 78 rpm (Box 9)
  - Tape cassettes
    - Ted Gomulka and his orchestra audio recording of Helen and Felix Kerszykowski wedding 1961, 2 audiocassettes 90 minutes (Box 9)
    - Red Octet, Dir. Ted Gomulka, "Our Pope-our shepherd", 1 audiocassettes (Box 9)
    - Ted Gomulka oral history recoded March 28, 1998, 1 audiocassettes 90 minutes (Box 9)
    - Johnny Sadrack's interview of Stan Wisniach on WMZK Radio 1975, 1 audiocassettes 90 minutes (Box 9)
    - Stan Wisniach on the Johnny Sadrack Polish show in Detroit 1975, 1 audiocassettes 90 minutes (Box 9)
    - WDET-102 FM program dedicated to Bob Zurke January 11, 1986, 1 audiocassettes 90 minutes (Box 9)
    - Unidentified, 1 audiocassettes 90 minutes (Box 9)
  - CD-ROMs
    - Stas Wisniach Club Polka Orchestra, 1 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 9)
  - 33 1/3-rpm phonograph discs
    - Ampol Aires, 1 phonograph records 33 1/3 rpm (Box 13)
    - Benny Boc Polka Tels, 1 phonograph records 33 1/3 rpm (Box 13)
    - Walt Cieslik and his musical ambassadors, 2 phonograph records 33 1/3 rpm (Box 13)
    - Impalas, 1 phonograph records 33 1/3 rpm (Box 13)
    - Ted Koltowicz and the sparks of fire, 1 phonograph records 33 1/3 rpm (Box 13)
    - Little Joe's Polka Play Boys, 1 phonograph records 33 1/3 rpm (Box 13)
    - Michigan Polka-Tels, 4 phonograph records 33 1/3 rpm (Box 13)
    - Johnny Sadrack and his orchestra, 1 phonograph records 33 1/3 rpm (Box 13)
    - Ted Sokolowski and his orchestra, 1 phonograph records 33 1/3 rpm (Box 13)
    - Stas and Margot, 1 phonograph records 33 1/3 rpm (Box 13)
    - Clare Witkowski and his orchestra, 3 phonograph records 33 1/3 rpm (Box 13)
  - Horn Man audio interviews on MC-90 microcassette tapes
    - Greg Adamus, 2 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Steve Brithinee, 2 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Bill and Virginia Bryden, 1 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - John C., 2 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Walt Cieslik, 2 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Wally Duda, 1 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Steve Dzoba, 2 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - John Gajec, 4 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Edwin Grzesik, 1 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Duayne Koltowic, 2 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Robert Kozaren, 2 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Eddie Krzyk, 2 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Walt Lipiec, 2 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Helen Nabozny, 2 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Panchito, 1 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Geri Sadrach, 1 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Sr. Mary Salome, 1 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Joe Skrzynski, 3 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Ernie Skuta, 1 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Stas Wisniach, 3 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Clare Wite, 2 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
    - Loretta (Guzik) Zandarelli, 1 audiocassettes microcassettes (Box 11)
- Promotional materials, certificates, etc.
  The Promotional materials, certificates, etc. series contains posters, promotional signs, and certificates issued to musicians.
  - City of Farmington, Mich. recognition certificate issued to Stanley J. "Stas" Wisniach (Box 12)
  - Club Polka poster (Box 12)
  - Dance Hall posters, 1930s-1960s, 14 items (Box 12)
  - Eddie Nabozny Hoyt's band promotional signs, 2 items (Box 12)
  - State of Michigan Polka Music Hall of Fame certificate issued to Marion (Mike) and Ann Buzinski (Box 12)
  - State of Michigan Polka Music Hall of Fame certificate issued to Deanna "Dee" Szalankiewicz Amsden, Dorothy A. Pickens, and Curtis M. Pickens (Box 12)
  - State of Michigan Polka Music Hall of Fame certificate issued to Eugene "Gene" Szalankiewicz (Box 12)
  - State of Michigan Polka Music Hall of Fame certificate issued to Clarence Witkowski (Box 12)
  - Take in some Polka Music at area Big Apple Bagels- oversize newspaper article, autographed (Box 12)
  - Ted Gomulka's band promotional signs circa 1960s-1980s, 3 items (Box 12)
  - Walt Cieslik's band promotional sign circa 1965 (Box 12)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual materials series consists of printed posters and hand-made signs advertising various performances. The series includes a photographed copy of the 1913 panoramic photograph of first Polish National Alliance convention in front of the East Side Dom Polski (The Polish House). Also included videotapes and a DVD with recorded performances and TV shows, as wells as interviews with musicians and their contemporaries.
  - Photographs
    - Ballroom photographs (Box 12)
    - Photographed copy of the 1913 panoramic photograph of first Polish National Alliance convention in front of the East Side Dom Polski (The Polish House) (Folder 1)
  - Videotapes, VHS tapes
    - Hornman footage 2003 (Box 10)
    - Interview with Thaddeus C. Radzilowski (Box 10)
    - Interview with Stas Wisniach, Greg Adamus, and Ralph Bowen 2004 (Box 10)
    - Jam sessions 2003 (Box 10)
    - At the Tip Top Field (Box 10)
    - Meet and greet: Live with Stas (Box 10)
    - Interviews for Review (Box 10)
  - Digital videocassettes
    - Miscellaneous videocassettes, identification unclear, 13 audiocassettes (Box 10)
  - DVD
    - Hornman Footage 2003 (Box 10)